Guide to the Patricia R. Cole and Nancy J. Flanakin National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence Records
University of Houston Libraries
Patricia R. Cole and Nancy J. Flanakin National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence Records
1977-2007
1998-2004
02/2011-007
National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence (U.S.)
8.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
The Patricia R. Cole and Nancy J. Flanakin National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence Records documents the organization’s work in providing training and consultation to organizations interested in the prevention of domestic and sexual violence. The collection includes correspondence, legal and legal style documentation, financial documents, printed materials, creative works, clippings, transparencies, forms, publications, posters, CDs, a VHS tape, note cards, handwritten notes, and ephemera created and maintained by The National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence (NCDSV). Because all records had been previously transferred from the organization to create a reference library at UT Austin, it was not possible to maintain original order. Additionally, the files of published literature in the field of domestic violence were removed as this material was deemed not an organic part of the organization's documentation. Where possible, folder contents were kept intact.
Historical Note:
Deborah Tucker and Sarah Buel formed the National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence (NCDSV) in 1998 to provide customized training and consultation on domestic and sexual violence issues at the national level. Both Tucker and Sarah come from strong backgrounds in the fight against domestic violence. In 1973, Tucker volunteered with the first rape crisis center in Texas. She became the Assistant Director of the Austin Rape Crisis Center and then became the Executive Director of the Austin Center for Battered Women from 1977 until 1982 (www.ncdsv.org). Tucker was the first Executive Director of the Texas Council on Family Violence, 1982 - 1996.
Sarah, herself a domestic violence survivor, has worked for more than 30 years with battered women and abused children within the legal system. Sarah is currently the Faculty Director of the Diane Halle Center for Family Justice at the Sandra Day O'Connor College of Law at Arizona State University. Prior to her current position she was a Clinical Professor at The University of Texas School of Law, having started, then co-directed, their Domestic Violence Clinic. She teaches "Domestic Violence and the Law", and some of her students’ papers have been included in the NCDSV records.
Deborah Tucker and Sarah Buel together formed a consulting firm in 1996 called Tucker, Buel, and Associates. The firm provided customized consultation and training to end violence against women. In May of 1998, the two women joined forces again and co-founded the National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence.
The organization has played a national role in several areas. It participated in the passage of the Violence Against Women Act, it collaborated in training with the National Sheriffs’ Association and the National Center for Rural Law Enforcement, and several staff members of the NCDSV participated in the Department of Defense Task Force on Domestic Violence (DTFDV). The National Defense Authorization Act established the DTFDV in 1999. Twelve senior members from the Department of Defense and twelve subject matter experts from the private sector comprised the members of the task force. The duty of the task force was to review and evaluate current Family Advocacy Programs and policies and make recommendations for improvement. The task force provided the Department of Defense with a strategic plan to improve domestic violence programs. Staff traveled to both Asian and European military installations to evaluate existing programs and to make recommendations. Tucker served as Co-Chair of this task force from 2000-2003.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence (U.S.)
Genre/Form of Material:
Articles; Clippings (information artifacts); Ephemera; Records (documents); Typescripts
Personal Name:
Buel, Sarah; Tucker, Debby
Topical Term:
Abused women -- Care; Family violence
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
The Patricia R. Cole and Nancy J. Flanakin National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence Records documents the organization’s work in providing training and consultation to organizations interested in the prevention of domestic and sexual violence. The collection includes correspondence, legal and legal style documentation, financial documents, printed materials, creative works, clippings, transparencies, forms, publications, posters, CDs, a VHS tape, note cards, handwritten notes, and ephemera created and maintained by The National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence (NCDSV). Because all records had been previously transferred from the organization to create a reference library at UT Austin, it was not possible to maintain original order. Additionally, the files of published literature in the field of domestic violence were removed as this material was deemed not an organic part of the organization's documentation. Where possible, folder contents were kept intact.
The records are arranged into six series with the bulk of the records dated 1998-2004. Administration, Conferences/Workshops, DTFDV (Defense Task Force on Domestic Violence), TCFV (Texas Council on Family Violence), Training/Education, and Tucker, Buel & Associates comprise the main series. The Administration series contains approximately half of the total records. Half of this first series consists of correspondence and a third consists of records of the co-founder, Sarah Buel.
The records are arranged into six series with the bulk of the records dated 1998-2004. Administration, Conferences/Workshops, DTFDV (Defense Task Force on Domestic Violence), TCFV (Texas Council on Family Violence), Training/Education, and Tucker, Buel & Associates comprise the main series. The Administration series contains approximately half of the total records. Half of this first series consists of correspondence and a third consists of records of the co-founder, Sarah Buel.
Administration records (1977-2007, 200 folders) are grouped into seven sub-series; Board of Directors, Donations, Executive Director, Memberships, Resume, Staff, and Staff Projects. Notable records include keynote speeches given by Sarah Buel at various conferences, Buel’s published works on domestic violence, and papers submitted by students of her “Domestic Violence and the Law” class taught during Buel’s time at the University of Texas Law School. Email threads in Nancy Flanakin’s correspondence reveal the NCDSV involvement in issues of national importance. An example of this is the 2004 correspondence showing the organizations involvement in reinstating the domestic violence exclusion in the Homeless Management Information System law. Under this act, domestic violence organizations were being forced to reveal shelter locations in order to sustain certain kinds of funding. Notable documents also include Patricia Cole’s work on welfare reform in regards to domestic violence victims and the Staff Bios contained in the Grant Proposal for Women’s Safety Initiative under the sub-series of Staff Projects.
The Conferences/Workshops records (1995-2005, 38 folders) contain conference folders or packets along with publications, printed material, forms, correspondence, ephemera, and handwritten notes. NCDSV members either participated in or attended the conferences/workshops listed. Notable records include Patricia Cole’s work on poverty and domestic violence at the Tenth Annual National Conference on Domestic Violence and Sarah Buel’s “Expert Witness” presentation at the 2001 Workshop of the same name.
The DTFDV (Defense Task Force on Domestic Violence) records (1996-2004, 101 folders) illuminate staff involvement during the three year period that DTFDV operated. This series is divided into four sub-series: Documents/Reports, Meetings, Site Visits, and Staff Documents. Under the sub-series “Meetings”, the April 2000 Initial Meeting documents the purpose, mission, and vision of the DTFDV.
The TCFV (Texas Council on Family Violence) records (1980-2007, 60 folders) are divided into six sub-series: Administration, Conferences, Ephemera, Manuals, National Domestic Hotline, and Reports/Documents. Both the Administration and Manuals sub-series contain important documents that NCDSV used as reference in creating its own organization and training methods.
The Training/Education series (1977-2007, 34 folders) is divided into four sub-series: Educational Materials, Handouts, Manuals, Slide/Presentations. A particularly chilling handout is a copy of a handwritten note containing a batterer’s rules for his victim.
The small series of Tucker, Buel & Associates contains records (1995-1998, 12 folders) created and maintained by NCDSV members. Items of interest include the materials from “A Domestic Violence Institute for Law Enforcement Trainers” and training materials for a coordinated community response to domestic violence.
The fonds deficiencies’ are that it does not contain founding documents, financial records particular to the NCDSV, and other administrative records.
Acronyms Employed in the Records and Finding Aid
BIPP: Batterer Intervention and Prevention Project
COBTH: Conference of Boston Teaching Hospitals
DTFDV: Defense Task Force on Domestic Violence
DOD: Department of Defense
DV: Domestic Violence
HASC: House Armed Services Committee
HMIS: Homeless Management Information System
LECC: Law Enforcement Coordinating Committee
NCADV: National Coalition Against Domestic Violence
NCDSV: National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence
NDVH: National Domestic Violence Hotline
NNEDV: National Network to End Domestic Violence
SOFA: Status-of-Forces Agreement
TANF: Temporary Assistance for Needy Families
TCFV: Texas Council on Family Violence
USAF: United States Air Force
VAWA: [National] Violence Against Women Act
Detailed List of Contents
- Administration, id123182
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence, legal and legal style documentation, receipts, printed materials, creative works, clippings, transparencies, charts, handwritten notes, and ephemera, 1977-2007 (200 folders) comprise the records in the Administration series. The series is divided into seven sub-series: Board of Directors, Donations, Executive Director, Memberships, Resume, Staff, and Staff Projects. The Board of Directors sub-series contains the records of three of the NCDSV board members: Sarah Buel, Rus Funk, and Toby Myers. The Staff sub-series consists of records of six staff members: Valinda Bolton, Patricia Cole, Nancy Flanakin, Vickie Smith, Christina Walsh, and Julie Walters. Correspondence contains not only the fax, email print-out, or letter, but also any documents referred to in the correspondence. The sub-series are arranged alphabetically and within that, the sub-sub-series are also alphabetical. At the lowest level the records have been arranged chronologically.
  - Board of Directors, id123188
    - Sarah M. Buel (Director Emeritus), id123189
      - Consultations, id123190
        - Testimony before US Senate, 1990; id123229 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        - Greenville County Grant, 1992; id123230 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - Correspondence, id123191
        - Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1987, 1991; id123232 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        - Boston Area Violence Prevention, 1991; id123233 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        - Immigrant battered women, 1993; id123234 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        - Health care response to DV, 1994; id123235 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        - Project Safe, 1994; id123236 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        - Ortho Video Project, 1994; id123237 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        - Jane Doe, et al. v. Purity Supreme, 1995; id123238 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        - American Medical Assoc., 1995; id123239 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - COBTH, 1995; id123240 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        - News article, 1997; id123241 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        - Migrant Clinicians Network, 1997; id123242 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        - Dept. of Health and Human Services, 1997; id123243 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        - “Divorce from Justice” article, 1998; id123244 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - Ambassador Programs, 1998; id123245 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Training on DV, 1999; id123246 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Creative Works, id123192
        - “Family Violence: Recommendations for Courts and Communities” draft, undated; id123248 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - “Domestic Violence: It Can Happen to Anyone”, 1993; id123249 (Box 1, Folder 19)
        - National College of District Attorneys, 1994-1995; id123250 (Box 1, Folder 20)
        - The Texas Prosecutor, 1996-1999; id123251 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - VAWA, 1998; id123252 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        - DV and the law, 1999-2000; id123253 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - Law School Education on DV, 2003; id123254 (Box 1, Folder 24)
        - Counsel for Battered Women, 2003; id123255 (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Educational/Training, id123193
        - Harvard Law School DV manual, undated; id123257 (Box 1, Folder 26)
        - DV Case Strategies for Prosecutors, undated; id123258 (Box 1, Folder 27)
        - Training remarks, undated; id123259 (Box 1, Folder 28)
        - Firearms and DV, undated; id123260 (Box 1, Folder 29)
        - Family Violence/Domestic Violence, undated, 1996; id123261 (Box 1, Folder 30)
        - Improving Medical Interventions, 1998; id123262 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      - Presentations, id123194
        - North Dakota Judicial Conference, 1993; id123265 (Box 1, Folder 32)
        - American Medical Assoc., 1994; id123266 (Box 1, Folder 33)
        - South Carolina Solicitors’ Assoc., 1995; id123267 (Box 1, Folder 34)
        - Annual Judicial Conference Of Michigan, 1996; id123268 (Box 1, Folder 35)
        - Montana Board of Crime Control, 1997; id123269 (Box 1, Folder 36)
        - DV Coalition of Greater Chattanooga, Inc., 1997; id123270 (Box 1, Folder 37)
        - Georgia Commission on Family Violence, 1997; id123271 (Box 2, Folder 1)
        - Victims of Violence, 1997; id123272 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Alaska Network on DV, 1998; id123273 (Box 2, Folder 3)
        - 4th Annual DV Conference for Professionals, 1998; id123274 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        - Fifth Annual Perinatal Partnership, 1998; id123275 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        - Air Force Family Advocacy Provider’s Conference, 2000; id123276 (Box 2, Folder 6-10)
      - Student Papers, id123195
        - DV and the Law, 1994-1995, 1997-2003; id123282 (Box 2, Folder 11-29)
    - Rus Ervin Funk (Secretary), id123196
      - Award Information, id123198
        - Acceptance Speech for the 2000 Frederick Douglass Award, id123302 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        - Leadership for a Changing World Nomination, 2002; id123303 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Creative Works, id123199
        - Leaving No Child Behind, 1997; id123305 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        - “What to do with men”, 1998; id123306 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        - “Partners in Healing: Working With Significant Others", 1999; id123307 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        - “Educational Programs to Reach Men” draft, 1999; id123308 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        - Date rape, 2000; id123309 (Box 3, Folder 7)
        - Coordinated response, 2000; id123310 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        - Prostitution, 2000; id123311 (Box 3, Folder 9)
        - Military vs. women (magazine article), 2001; id123312 (Box 3, Folder 10)
        - Impact of sexism, 2004; id123313 (Box 3, Folder 11-13)
        - Sexual Assault Report, 2005; id123316 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Documents, id123200
        - Future for advocacy, undated; id123318 (Box 3, Folder 15)
        - Zorza paper with Funk Comments, undated; id123319 (Box 3, Folder 16)
        - Various Documents, 2000, undated; id123320 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Toby Myers (Vice-Chair), id123197
      - Clipping - Houston Breakthrough, 1978; id123322 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Consultation: Expert witness contributor, 2005; id123323 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Correspondence, 1992, 2005; id123324 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Formal Paper on sex roles, 1977; id123325 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Published Work, 1997; id123326 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Donations, id123201
    - Jane’s Due Process, id123202
      - Jane’s Due Process organizational documents, 2001, 2003; id123328 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Executive Director – Deborah Tucker, id123203
      - Award: Teaching Tolerance, 2002; id123331 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Clippings – New York Times, 2004; id123332 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Correspondence, 1987, 1994, 1996-2004, undated; id123359 (Box 3, Folder 26-51)
      - Notes, undated; id123385 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Publications with Tucker Quotes, 1997, 2002-2005; id123386 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
      - Published Works, 2003; id123388 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Memberships, id123204
      - NCADV, 2000; id123390 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - National Center for Women and Policing, 2001; id123391 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Center for Research on Women, 2002; id123392 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Survivors in Service, 2002; id123393 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - National Center for Victims of Crimes, 2004; id123394 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Resume, id123205
      - Edward Brandt Resume, undated; id123396 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Staff, id123206
      - Valinda Bolton (Military Project Coordinator, Training Director), id123208
        - Correspondence, 1999, 2000, 2003; id123398 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Patricia Cole (Assistant Director), id123209
        - Correspondence, undated, 1999-2002; id123400 (Box 4, Folder 12)
        - Published works: welfare in regards to DV victims, 1997-1998, 2000-2001, undated; id123401 (Box 4, Folder 13-18)
        - Reviews, 1998, undated; id123407 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Nancy Flanakin (Library Coordinator), id123210
        - Battered Women in Prison Project, 2006; id123410 (Box 4, Folder 20-21)
        - Class visits, 2006; id123412 (Box 4, Folder 22)
        - Correspondence, 2001-2004; id123413 (Box 4, Folder 23-34)
        - Correspondence, 2004-2007; id123425 (Box 5, Folder 1-14)
        - Diversity Institute, undated, 2005-2006; id123439 (Box 5, Folder 15)
        - Domestic Violence, Welfare, and Poverty Bibliography, 2004; id123440 (Box 5, Folder 16)
        - Job Description at SSW, undated, 2005; id123441 (Box 5, Folder 17)
        - Library relocation to SSW, 2005-2006; id123442 (Box 5, Folder 18)
        - Listservs subscription information, 2003-2006; id123443 (Box 5, Folder 19)
        - Orders under consideration, 2003-2006; id123444 (Box 5, Folder 20)
        - Quotes from Nancy, 2003; id123445 (Box 5, Folder 21)
        - Receipts/Orders, 2006-2007; id123446 (Box 5, Folder 22)
        - Reviews, undated, 2002-2005; id123447 (Box 5, Folder 23-32)
        - Student Contact Sheets, 2006; id123457 (Box 5, Folder 33)
        - Thank-yous, 2006; id123458 (Box 5, Folder 34)
        - Time and leave, 2006; id123459 (Box 5, Folder 35)
      - Vickie Smith (Training Coordinator, Deputy Director), id123211
        - Correspondence, 2000, 2003; id123461 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        - Reviews, 2003, 2004; id123462 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - Christina Walsh (Technical Assistance Director, Communications Director), id123212
        - Clipping: Nurseweek, 2001; id123464 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        - Correspondence, 1999, 2000, 2002-2005; id123465 (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Julie Walters (Sexual Assault Projects Director), id123213
        - Correspondence, undated, 2004, 2005; id123467 (Box 6, Folder 5)
        - Publication with Walters quotes, 2004; id123468 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Staff Projects, id123207
      - Doors of Hope Project, 1998-1999; id123470 (Box 6, Folder 7)
      - Agenda for the Nation drafts with comments, 1999-2000; id123471 (Box 6, Folder 8-10)
      - Betty Lou Beets - clippings, 2000; id123474 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Grant Proposal for Women’s Safety Initiative, 2000; id123475 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Proposal for Program for Prosecutors, 2001; id123476 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Sex Trafficking, 2004; id123477 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Conferences/Workshops, id123183
  Correspondence, publications, printed materials, forms, handwritten notes, and ephemera, 1995-2005 (38 folders) comprise the records in the Conferences/Workshop series. The series details the NCDSV's participation in or attendance of conferences (including web conferences and teleconferences) and workshops. The items in this series are arranged chronologically.
  - Visualizing the Future without Domestic Violence, 1995/1996; id123480 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Domestic Violence in Latin America and the Caribbean, 1997; id123481 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - World Conference on Family Violence, 1997; id123482 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Technical Assistance, 1998; id123483 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Grantmakers conference, 1999; id123484 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - The Next Millennium Conference, 1999; id123485 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Florida Coalition Against Domestic Violence, 1999; id123486 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - TCFV Let’s Get Real, 2000; id123487 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - National Sexual Violence Prevention Conference, 2000; id123488 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Improving Criminal Justice Center’s Response, 2000; id123489 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - LECC Executive Summit 2000, id123490 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Tenth Annual National Conference on Domestic Violence, 2000; id123491 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Advocacy In and Out of the System, 2000; id123492 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - DV Training for Rural Officers, 2000; id123493 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Stalking Package, 2000; id123494 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Changing Role of Law Enforcement in Ending Violence Against Women, 2000; id123495 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Stalking Package, 2000; id123496 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - NTCDSV Conference presentation, 2001; id123497 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - ProTex statewide conference, 2001; id123498 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Multi-Cultural Forum on Violence Against Women, 2001; id123499 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Building Solutions with Chemically Addicted Clients, 2001; id123500 (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Trapped by Poverty/Trapped By Abuse, 2001; id123501 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - NTCDSV Workshop – Expert Witness, 2001; id123502 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Evaluating Systems presentation, 2002; id123503 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Violence Against Women, 2002; id123504 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Emerge - 2002, id123505 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Advanced Facilitations Skills Workshop, 2003; id123506 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
  - Trapped by Poverty/Trapped By Abuse, 2003; id123508 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - WomensLaw.org Strategic Planning Meeting, 2004; id123509 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Teleconference hosted by NNEDV on HMIS, 2004; id123510 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Teleconference hosted by VAWnet on housing, 2004; id123511 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Fatality Review Audioconference, 2004; id123512 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Emerge 2005, id123513 (Box 7, Folder 11-12)
  - Jewish Women International, 2005; id123515 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Web Conference – Toward a Community Solution, 2005; id123516 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Coordinated Response to Domestic Violence on Military Bases, 2005; id123517 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- DTFDV (Defense Task Force on Domestic Violence), id123184